Guide to the Connecticut Miscellanea 1884-1933 MS 012 MS 012 MS 012 MS 012
Cornwall Historical Society
Connecticut Miscellanea
1884-1933
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS 012
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
This collection was gathered by Cornwall historian E.C. Starr, and relates to the general history of Connecticut.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The overwhelming majority of the items in the collection are publications gathered by Starr during his lifetime.
Scope and Content Note
This collection was gathered by Cornwall historian E.C. Starr, and relates to the general history of Connecticut. The overwhelming majority of the items in the collection are publications gathered by Starr during his lifetime. The collection is organized into three sections devoted to books, articles, and miscellaneous items.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged tpoically or by town, then chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 27 series:
Books
Articles
Miscellaneous
Canaan
Centerbrook
Colebrook
Goshen
Guilford
Kent
Litchfield
Madison
Mattatuck
Morris
New Bitain
New Milford
Norfolk
Northfield
North Stanford
Salisbury
Sharon
Sheffield, MA.
Terryville
Thomaston
Torrington
Warren
Washington
Winchester
Slavery--United States; Articles; Sharon (Conn.)--history.; Salisbury (Conn.)--history.; Canaan (Conn.)--history.; Winchester (Conn.)--history.; Washington (Conn.)--history.; Warren (Conn.)--history.; Torrington (Conn.)--history.; Thomaston (Conn.)--history.; Terryville (Conn.)--history.; Sheffield (Mass.)--history.; North Stamford (Conn.)--history.; Norfolk (Conn.)--history.; New Milford (Conn.)--history.; New Britain (Conn.)--history.; Morris (Conn.)--history.; Madison (Conn.)--history.; Litchfield (Conn.)--history.; Kent (Conn.)--history.; Guilford (Conn.)--history.; Goshen (Conn.)--history.; Colebrook (Conn.)--history.; Centerbrook (Conn.)--history.; concert programs; invitations; Pamphlets; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Hartford courant
- Books
  - Sketch of Connecticut centenarians written by Frederick H. Nash, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - “Litchfield County Connecticut, or One Rural County’s Contributions to the Nation’s Power and Fame” by H. Clay Trumbull, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles
  - “Slaves In The State,” The Courant, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “60 Towns In Vermont Celebrate 150th Anniversary,” The Connecticut Courant, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - “Early Connecticut Silver Told Of By George M. Curtis Of Meriden,” The Hartford Courant, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - “Connecticut And Her Old Charter,” The Hartford Courant, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - “Child Executed In This State,” The Hartford Courant, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - “Life In Early Days Of Colony,” The Hartford Courant, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - “Now Quiet Rural Town, Lebanon Played Heroic Role During Revolution,” The Hartford Daily Courant, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous
  - Notice about Connecticut Old Home Week Association, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Connecticut Tercentennial Pamphlet Series, 1933-1936 (Box 2)
- Canaan
  - Centennial celebration hymn lyrics from South Canaan, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Program for Conn. Library Association meeting at Fall’s Village, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Program for installation of Rev. Charles W. Hanna at East Canaan, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Manual for Pilgrim Church, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Front page from Congregational congress meeting program, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Invitation sent to Cornwall’s First Church members to attend Pilgrim Church’s anniversary, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Program for Pilgrim Church’s 25th anniversary celebration, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper article, “Pilgrim Church Has Double Celebration", 1912 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lenten season schedule for Pilgrim Church, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - New Year’s greetings and announcements from Rev. Edwin C. Gillette, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper article, “Interesting Sketch of the Town of North Canaan", 1921 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Invitation to special services at Pilgrim Church, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Notice for Thursday lectures given at Pilgrim Church, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Announcement of hymn singing meeting hosted by the Canaan Choral Society, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Invitation to attend East Canaan Congregational Church services, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Pilgrim Church 25th anniversary booklet, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper article on “Canaan’s Iron and Lime", undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Manual for East Canaan Congregational Church, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Booklet, “Vicissitudes of the East Canaan Church", undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Pilgrim Church notes, mentioning E.C. Starr, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Newspaper clipping, “Settling Old Canaan", undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Centerbrook
  - Second Meeting House centenary program, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Colebrook
  - Invitation to Congregational Church’s 100th anniversary, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Goshen
  - Collection of deeds related to the “Gardiner Place", 1808-1850 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Annual selectmen and treasurer report, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Dedication of Congregational Church, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Church Building Quarterly with article on Congregational Church, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Program, poster, and ticket for “The Holy City,” performed by Goshen Choral Class, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 28-30)
  - Program and poster for “The Banner of St. George,” performed by Goshen Choral Class, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
  - Program for Goshen Choral Class, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Poster for “The Sun = Worshippers,” performed by Goshen Choral Class, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - A History of South End, Goshen, Connecticut by Hervey Brooks, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Guilford
  - Circular pamphlet of the Congregational Church, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Program for town's 250th anniversary, 1889 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Booklet on Congregational Church’s 250th anniversary, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Image of “The Old Stone House", 1900 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Program for the installation of Rev. Warren D. Bigelow, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Annual town report, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Historical sketch of church music, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Newspaper clipping on sleighing party of 1856, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Kent
  - Congregational Church manual, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Treasurer’s report of ecclesiastical society, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Program for teacher’s meeting, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Program for installation of Rev. Herbert K. Job, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Newspaper article on town bicentennial, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Litchfield
  - Anonymous letter about taxes, 1791 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Bishop family deeds, 1866-1872 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - First Congregational Church manual, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Program for ordination of Rev. George C. Woodruff, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Invitation and program to Rev. Wesley E. Page ordination in Milton, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Article on “The Litchfield Law School", 1901 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Article on “Life In Old Litchfield", 1906 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Reports of the Litchfield Historical Society, 1909-1920 (Box 3, Folder 56-61)
  - Article on Litchfield County bar banquet, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - The Litchfield Enquirer Vol. LXXXV, No. 47, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Article on restored Litchfield Law School, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Newspaper photograph of “A Litchfield April Ice Storm", 1914 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - List of Litchfield Historical Society members, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - “Constitution and By-Laws of the Litchfield Historical Society", 1914 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Postcard sent to Mr. C.B. Bishop, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Sermon, “Judah Champion” preached at Congregational Church, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Historical address on “St. Michael’s Parish", 1919 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Invitation sent to E.C. Starr to Henry Ward Beecher’s 100th birthday commemoration, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Newspaper clipping listing Revolutionary War soldiers, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Postcard with image of Litchfield Law School, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
- Madison
  - Historical booklet on Congregational Church, 1878 (Box 3, Folder 74)
- Mattatuck
  - Newspaper story on historical society, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 75)
- Morris
  - Issues of The Morris Herald, 1899-1901 (Box 3, Folder 76-77)
  - Newspaper article on town history, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, regarding town history, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 79)
- New Britain
  - Booklet for Methodist Epworth League, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 80)
- New Milford
  - History of First Congregational Church, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Program and summary of First Congregational Church Bi-Centennial, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 82-83)
- Norfolk
  - Congregational Church manual, 1858 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Commemorative booklets from installation of Rev. William F. Stearns, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Religious Herald with cover photo of Norfolk, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Church of Christ annual reports, 1900-1908 (Box 4, Folder 4-8)
  - By-laws of Norfolk Glee Club, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Commemorative items from Congregational Church’s 150th anniversary, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - Booklet on place-names in Norfolk, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Lincoln Memorial Concert programs, 1912-1927 (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
  - Text of historical address given to medical association by John H. Kendall, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Program for installation of Rev. W.B. Johnson, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Text of sermon preached by Rev. H.C. Robbins, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Programs for music show given by Norfolk Home Missionary Society, 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
  - Newspaper story about Yale Music School, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Cover page from the Norfolk Inn, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Order of Congregational Church morning service, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Postcard with image of Norfolk Library, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Travel booklet with images of Norfolk, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper clipping, “Unusual Interest in Concerts in Norfolk", undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Northfield
  - Congregational Church manual, 1875 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Congregational Church booklet, “Christian Work", 1885 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- North Stamford
  - Booklet commemorating centennial celebration of Congregational Church, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Salisbury
  - Congregational Church centennial celebration booklet, 1844 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Letter from Rev. John C. Goddard to his congregation, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Congregational Church 150th anniversary items, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 32-33)
  - Church of Christ pastoral reports, 1895-1921 (Box 4, Folder 34-41)
  - Teacher’s meeting program, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - The Religious Herald with cover photo of Church of Christ, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Congregational Church building centennial celebration program, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Sermon, “The Litchfield Samson,” by John C. Goddard, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Newspaper article, “Limestone Caves at Twin Lakes", 1909 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Church of Christ Easter Week service schedule, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Booklet, “Historic Iron Making in Connecticut", 1914 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Annual report of selectmen and town officers, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Church of Christ Holy Week schedule, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Article on inter-faith meeting held in town, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Invitation sent to E.C. Starr by church committee to sit on Ecclesiastical Council, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Program for the installation of Rev. Roger E. Treat, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Booklet, “Salisbury,” by John Calvin Goddard, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Tract, “Experience of a Country Town,” by John Calvin Goddard, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Salisbury Fair program, undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
- Sharon
  - Poll tax notice sent to tax collector, William Everett, 1840 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Booklet, “About an Old New England Church,” by Gerald Stanley Lee, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Program for teacher’s meeting, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper article on mortuary chapel, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Program for ordination of Rev. Robert B. Street, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Booklet for Congregational Church’s 100th anniversary, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Program for Congregational Church meeting, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Sheffield, Mass.
  - Account book of John Crosby, 1822-1828 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Terryville
  - Manual for Congregational Church, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Thomaston
  - Newspaper clipping on Thomaston funeral of Cornwall native Harvey Baldwin, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Thomaston High School commencement program, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Program for Marine Band concert, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Torrington
  - Program for Torringford Congregational Church 125th anniversary, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Souvenir booklet from installation of Rev. James A. Chamberlain at Center Church, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Editorial criticizing Torrington native Simeon Baldwin, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper story on birth of John Brown, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Program for Center Church, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Torringford Congregational Church ordination service of Mr. and Mrs. Hawthorne Jones program, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Warren
  - Newspaper article on church restoration and program for Congregational Church’s 150th anniversary, 1906-1939 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Washington
  - Premium lists from Fair Corporation, 1916-1922 (Box 5, Folder 20-22)
- Winchester
  - Manual from the Second Congregational Church of West Winsted, 1882 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Issues of “The Messenger,” published by Second Congregational Church of West Winsted, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 24-31)
  - Second Congregational Church of West Winsted annual record, 1897-1898 (Box 5, Folder 32-33)
  - Invitation and programs for 40th anniversary service of Rev. A. Goodenough, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 34-35)
  - Newspaper article on Rev. Arthur Goodenough, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Program and collections list for Winchester Congregational Church, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Booklet, “Twenty-Five Years in Winsted,” about YMCA, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Text of address, “A New England Village Green,” delivered at historical society, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Winsted Second Congregational Church booklet, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Invitation sent to E.C. Starr to attend Winchester’s 150th anniversary, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 41)